Guide to the Leopold Haimson papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Menshevik Project,1890s-1977(Inter-University Project on the History of Menshevik Movement)
  - Subseries III.3: Archive on the History of Menshevism, 1898-1972
    - Sub-subseries III.3.8: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik Records, 1941-1964
      - Editorial materials:
        - 1958
          - #11
            - Typescripts for typesetting; drafts of articles, (typescripts with holograph notes unless otherwise noted)
              - Nikolaevsky, Boris. "K istorii stalinskikh chistok: Dopolnitel'nyi - 51-yi - tom BSE" (Box 64, Folder 9)
              - Ol'berg, P. "Shvetsiia i Boris Pasternak: Pis'mo iz Stokgol'ma", (holograph and typed copies) (Box 64, Folder 7)
              - Schwarz, Solomon. "Na puti k semiletnemu planu" (Box 64, Folder 8)
              - Vishniak, Mark. "Novaia konstitutsiia Frantsii" (Box 64, Folder 9)
              - Voitinskii, Vladimir. (aka Woytinsky, W.) "Nishcheta ekonomicheskoi mysli", (holograph draft and typescript) (Box 64, Folder 8)
            - Final revises with holograph notes (Box 64, Folder 10)
            - Galley proofs with holograph notes: see Series XVI: Oversize materials--Subseries XVI.2: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik--Editorial materials (Box 168, Folder 8)
          - #12 (December)
            - Typescripts for typesetting, (typescripts with holograph notes unless otherwise noted)
              - Abramovich, Rafael. "Sama sebia raba b'et" (Box 64, Folder 11)
              - Aleksandrova, Vera. "Neveselye mysli pered 3-im s'ezdom pisatelei" (Box 64, Folder 12)
              - Denike, Iurii. "Rezul'taty frantsuzskikh vyborov", (holograph manuscript) (Box 64, Folder 12)
              - Nikolaevsky, Boris. "Pered XXI s'ezdom KPSS" (Box 64, Folder 11)
              - Schwarz, Solomon. "Vokrug semiletki" (Box 64, Folder 11)
              - Vishniak, Mark. "Doktor Zhivago" i ego tolkovateli" (Box 64, Folder 12)
              - Voitinskii, Vladimir. (aka Woytinsky, W.) "Nishcheta ekonomicheskoi mysli v SSSR: o knige E. Vargi "Osnovnye voprosy ekonomiki i politiki imperializma [Posle vtoroi mirovoi voiny]" (Box 64, Folder 12)
            - Final revises and galley proofs with holograph notes: Series XVI: Oversize materials--Subseries XVI.2: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik--Editorial materials (Box 168, Folders 9-10)
        - 1959
          - #1 (January)
            - Typescripts for typesetting, (typescripts with holograph notes unless otherwise noted)
              - Abramovich, Rafael. "Zachem Mikoian priekhal v SSHA?" (Box 64, Folder 13)
              - Aleksandrova, Vera. "Kolkhoznaia 'ottepel'"?" (Box 64, Folder 14)
              - "Avtoportret Trotskogo" (Box 64, Folder 14)
              - Borokhovich, E. "Amerikanskie vybory i professional'nye soiuzy" (Box 64, Folder 14)
              - Burg, D. "Shkol'naia reforma" (Box 64, Folder 13)
              - Denike, Iurii. "Diskussiia o zashchite demokratii i sotsializma", (holograph manuscript) (Box 64, Folder 14)
              - "Gromyko o Palestine" (Box 64, Folder 14)
              - "Pamiati E.D. Kuskovoi" (Box 64, Folder 13)
              - Schwarz, Solomon. "Na agrarnom fronte: Dekabr'skii plenum TSK kompartii" (Box 64, Folder 13)
            - Final revises and galley proofs with holograph notes: see Series XVI: Oversize materials--Subseries XVI.2: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik--Editorial materials (Box 169, Folder 1)
          - #2-3:
            - Typescripts for typesetting, (typescripts with holograph notes unless otherwise noted)
              - Abramovich, Rafael. "Nakanune sud'bonosnykh reshenii" (Box 64, Folder 15)
              - Aleksandrova, Vera. "Sovremennost', partiinost' i masterstvo" (Box 64, Folder 15)
              - Burg, D. "O chem. shel spor na 21-om s'ezde KPSS" (Box 64, Folder 15)
              - Denike, Iurii. "Politicheskii smysl khrushchevskoi mifologii", (holograph manuscript) (Box 64, Folder 15)
              - "Kak Khrushchev ne vmeshivaetsia vo vnutrennie dela drugikh stran" (Box 64, Folder 16)
              - Nikolaevsky, Boris. "K itogam XXI s'ezda KPSS" (Box 64, Folder 15)
              - "Pod znakom pravogo nigilizma" (Box 64, Folder 16)
              - Schwarz, Solomon. "Semiletka" (Box 64, Folder 15)
              - Skorbnyi listok: S.A. Magin; T.I. Vulikh (Box 64, Folder 16)
              - "Sorbonna v Moskve", (holograph manuscript) (Box 64, Folder 16)
              - Valentinov, Nikolai. "Dopolnenie k "Dnevniku" Trotskogo" (Box 64, Folder 16)
              - "Zagadki s'ezda kompartii" (Box 64, Folder 16)
            - Galley proofs with holograph notes: see Series XVI: Oversize materials--Subseries XVI.2: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik--Editorial materials (Box 169, Folder 2)
        - 1962 #11-12
          - Typescripts for typesetting and drafts of articles, (typescripts with holograph notes unless otherwise noted)
            - Bialer, Seweryn. "Economic background of Khrushchev's reorganization" (Box 65, Folder 2)
            - I.M. "Oppozitsionnye nastroeniia moskovskogo studenchestva v seredine dvadtsatykh godov" (Box 65, Folder 1)
            - Nikolaevsky, Boris. "Novyi krutoi povorot Khrushcheva" (Box 65, Folder 1)
            - Obozrevatel'. "Anti-staliniana", (typescript of article with holograph notes) (Box 65, Folder 2)
            - "Razdor v kommunisticheskom lagere", (holograph manuscript and typescript) (Box 65, Folder 1)
          - Galley proofs with holograph notes: see Series XVI: Oversize materials--Subseries XVI.2: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik--Editorial materials (Box 169, Folder 3)
        - 1963
          - #1/2
            - Typescripts for typesetting and drafts of articles, (typescripts with holograph notes unless otherwise noted)
              - Abramovich, Rafael. "De Goll' i Degolizm", (holograph manuscript) (Box 65, Folder 3)
              - Aleksandrova, Vera. "Trevoga na fronte literatury i iskusstva" (Box 65, Folder 3)
              - Denike, Iurii. "Krizis v zapadnoi koalitsii", (holograph manuscript and typescript with holograph notes) (Box 65, Folder 3)
              - Obozrevatel'. "Bol'shaia chistka" glazami sovremennikov" (Box 65, Folder 4)
              - Schwarz, Solomon. "K sotsiologii Kompartii" (Box 65, Folder 4)
              - Tigrid, Pavel. "Ten' Slanskogo" (Box 65, Folder 4)
            - Final revises and galley proofs with holograph notes (incomplete): see Series XVI: Oversize materials--Subseries XVI.2: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik--Editorial materials (Box 169, Folders 4-5)
          - #7-8:
            - Typescripts for typesetting with holograph notes
              - Bialer, Seweryn. "SSSR na novom puti?" (Box 65, Folder 5)
              - "Karl Marks kak issledovatel': K 80-letiiu so dnia smerti Marksa" (Box 65, Folder 5)
              - "Khrushchev i 'vnutrennie kitaitsy'" (Box 65, Folder 6)
              - Kersten, Geints. "Otgoloski sovetskikh sobytii v Vostochnoi Germanii" (Box 65, Folder 6)
              - Schwarz, Solomon. "Tri etapa" (Box 65, Folder 6)
            - Final revises with holograph notes: see Series XVI: Oversize materials--Subseries XVI.2: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik--Editorial materials (Box 169, Folder 6)
        - 1964
          - Sbornik #1
            - Typescripts for typesetting, (typescripts with holograph notes unless otherwise noted)
              - Aleksandrova, Vera. "Vozvrashchenie cheloveka" (Box 65, Folder 7)
              - Denike, Iurii. "Amerika posle Kennedi", (holograph manuscript) (Box 65, Folder 7)
              - Gal'perin, Ernst. "Dilemma Fidelia Kastro: Pis'mo iz Gavany" (Box 65, Folder 8)
                (including copy in English and 2 letters from S.Schwarz to Tat'iana Pavlovna regarding translation)
              - Obozrevatel'. Zhenschiny sredi sovetskoi elity (Box 65, Folder 8)
              - Schwarz, Solomon:
                - "K voprosu o formirovanii men'shevizma i bol'shevizma: Organizatsionnye problemy sotsialdemokratii v 1904-1905godakh" (Box 65, Folder 9)
                - "Meniaetsia litso sel'skokhoziaistvennogo plenuma TsK" (Box 65, Folder 9)
                - "Protivorechiia sovetskoi sel'skokhoziaistvennoi politiki" (Box 65, Folder 9)
              - Veber, German. "Moi put'" (Box 65, Folder 9)
              - Vishniak, Mark. Novaia ideia Khrushcheva - "obshchenarodnoe gosudarstvo" (Box 65, Folder 10)
            - Galley proofs with holograph notes: see Series XVI: Oversize materials--Subseries XVI.2: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik--Editorial materials, Box 169, Folder 7
          - Sbornik #2
            - Table of content (Box 65, Folder 11)
            - Drafts of articles, (typescripts with holograph notes unless otherwise noted)
              - Bialer, Seweryn:
                - "Nationalities in the Soviet Elite, 1939-1963" (Box 65, Folder 11)
                - "Ukraintsy v sovetskoi elite" (Box 65, Folder 11)
              - Denike, Iurii. "Dzhonson i Golduoter", (holograph manuscript) (Box 65, Folder 11)
              - Schwarz, Solomon:
                - "Evreiskii vopros v ramkakh sovetskoi politiki natsional'nostei" (Box 65, Folder 12-13)
                - "Krizis mezhdunarodnogo kommunizma" (Box 65, Folder 12)
          - Galley proofs with holograph notes: see Series XVI: Oversize materials--Subseries XVI.2: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik--Editorial materials, Box 169, Folder 8
    - Sub-subseries III.3.9: Periodicals Collection
      Acquisition of Menshevik publications, newspapers, and magazines was one of the major elements of the Project. Periodicals were collected in various available formats as originals, photocopies, and microfilms. Files of this sub-subseriescontain a list of the Project holdings (incomplete) and references to the bibliography of Menshevik periodicals.
      Periodicals belonging to the Project, as well as other periodicals and serial publications from Leopold Haimson Papers, are in a process of been cataloged by individual title (as of the February 2009). Originals and photocopies are cataloged for the SEEC collection (Soviet and East European Collection of printed materials in the Bakhmeteff archive) and will be available in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library upon completion of the cataloging process. Periodicals preserved on microfilms will be available in the Microform Reading Room.
      For the comprehensive list of periodicals click here (or see Appendix 1 in the paper copy of the finding aid).
      - List of project holdings (Box 65, Folder 14)
      - Catalog: see Series X: Research and Reference materials--Subseries X.1: Bibliographies--Card catalog (Boxes 102-114)
      - Alphabetical list of periodicals and serials: click here or see Appendix 1 in the paper copy of the finding aid
    - Sub-subseries III.3.10: Microfilm Collection (Box 65)
      Microfilms belonging to the Menshevik project contain a variety of materials related to the history of the Menshevik movement: periodicals, books, archival materials from Soviet archives and libraries. Files of this sub-subseries include a list of the Project's holdings (incomplete) and references to the card catalog that contains information on holdings.
      Microfilms belonging to the Project, as well as other microfilms from Leopold Haimson Papers, are in a process of been cataloged by individual title (as of the February 2009). Upon completion of the cataloging process they will be available in the Microform Reading Room.
      For the comprehensive list of microfilms click here (or see Appendix 2 in the paper copy of the finding aid).
      There is some number of microfilm reels with unidentified materials that may content documents and letters related to the history of Menshevism. These microfilms are part of the Series X: Research and Reference Materials (box 147-A).
      - List of project holdings (Box 65, Folder 15-16)
      - Varia (Box 65, Folder 16)
      - Catalog: see Series X: Research and Reference materials--Subseries X.1: Bibliographies--Card catalog--Microfilms, Box 115
      - Alphabetical list of microfilms: click here or see Appendix 2 in the paper copy of the finding aid
    - Sub-subseries III.3.11: Audiomaterials, 1960s
      Audio records of interviews with Georgian Mensheviks, the reading of N. Zhordania's memoirs, and seminar discussions. Reel-to-reel tapes stored along with other audio materials from the collection in Series XIV: Audio Materials (boxes 161-162).
      - Interviews: (Box 161-162)
        - Arsenidze, Razhden. Interviews #1-5, (5 reels) (Box 161)
        - Eradze, Georgii. Interviews #5-8; 11-18, (6 reels) (Box 161)
        - Tsuladze, Vasilii (Box 161)
        - Zhordania, Inna, (3 reels) (Box 161)
        - Russian interviews of 1968, (9 reels) (Box 162)
          (these interviews may not be related to the Menshevik project)
      - Memoirs reading: Zhordania, Noah. Memoirs, (1 reel) (Box 161)
        (read by Ina Zhordania)
      - Seminars:
        - 1962 Schwarz seminar of December 18: Discussion of "Osnovnaia kontseptsiia revoliutsii", (1 reel) (Box 162)
        - 1964
          - Lande seminar of January, 25: Discussion of his work, (1 reel) (Box 162)
          - Denike seminar of April 11: Discussion of his work, (2 reels) (Box 162)
          - Volin seminar ofMay 2: Discussion of chapters 6 and 7 of his work, (1 reel) (Box 162)
        - 1968 Untitled seminar of May 20, (1 reel-to-reel) (Box 161)
- Series IV: Strikes Project, 1980s
  This series contains materials from the cooperative project that was launched in 1982 after an international colloquium in comparative labor history in Paris. The participants in the colloquium decided to pursue a discussion of analytic problems addressed in its proceedings, and to explore further possibilities of analyzing them in a comparative perspective through the application of quantitative methods. An international working group was created for this purpose. An international cooperative framework was established involving the Maison des Sciences de l'Homme (Paris), the International Research and Exchanges Board (New York), the Academy of Sciences of the USSR, and the eventual cooperation of the Friedrich Ebert and Feltrinelli Foundations. The tasks pursued by this Project included the creation of an international data bank to make available, in computer readable form, the statistical data on industrial labor conflicts recorded in the official and other major sources for Austria-Hungary, France, Great Britain, Italy, Germany, Imperial Russia, and the United States; the organization, under the sponsorship of the Project, of other colloquia in the field of comparative labor history; and the joint publication program. The series is arranged in three subseries and includes Project documents, writings, and research material. Related to the Project materials located also in Series VI: Colloquiua and Conferences.
  - Subseries IV.1: Project Documentation
    Files contain project description, grant proposals, budget notes, and data. Not arranged.
    - Project Documentation (Box 66, Folder 1-2)
  - Subseries IV.2: Monographs and colloquium papers, 1982-1992
    Comprises typescripts with holograph notes and correction; drafts and notes of the Project publications and papers presented at the international colloquium. Arranged in alphabetical order by volume's title, then alphabetically by author's name.
    - Monographs and colloquium papers, 1982-1992 (Box 66, Folder 1-2)
    - Annales volume, [1982]
      - Drafts, charts (Box 66, Folder 3-7)
      - Manuscript
        - Haimson, Leopold; Petrusha, Ronald. "Strike waves in Imperial Russia (1912-14, 1905-07): a quantitive analysis and interpretation" (Box 66, Folder 3-7)
        - Hogan, Heather. "Industrial rationalization and the roots of labor militance in the St. Peterburg metal-working industry, 1901-1914" (Box 66, Folder 3-7)
        - Koenker, Diana. "Strikes in revolution: Russia, 1917" (Box 66, Folder 3-7)
    - Annales volume, [1982] (continuation) (Box 67, Folder 1-4)
    - Haimson, Leopold; Petrusha, Ronald. "Strikes in Russia, 1895-1914a summary and interpretation of the results of a quantitive analysis", (manuscript, notes on discussion, pertinent correspondence) (Box 67, Folder 5-8)
    - Haimson, Leopold. "Two strikes waves in Imperial Russia (1905-1907 1912-1914): Finding and interpretations of a quantitative analysis" (Box 68, Folder 1-2)
    - Papers presented at the Colloquium on the Comparative History of Strikes, 1982 Paris
      - Bezza, Bruno. "Transformation des statuts professionnels pendant la premiere guerre mondiale et le nouveau modele des relations industrielles" (Box 68, Folder 3)
      - Bovykin, Viktor:
        - "Napravlenie i problemy statisticheskogo izucheniia stachek rabochikh v tsarskoi Rossii" (Box 68, Folder 4)
        - "Tendances et les problemes de l'etude statistique des greves ouvrieres en Russie Tsariste" (Box 68, Folder 4)
      - Costas, Ilse:
        - "Summary of questions addressed, the data and methods used, and the conclusions reached in my studies of labour unrest" (Box 68, Folder 5)
        - "Topics, problems, approaches which should be incorporated into the discussion" (Box 68, Folder 5)
      - Cronin, James. "Strikes and power in Britain, 1870-1920" (Box 68, Folder 6)
      - Edwards, Paul. "General themes" (Box 68, Folder 7)
      - Franzosi, Roberto. "One hundred years of strike statistics: data, methodology, and theoretical issues in quantitative strike research" (Box 68, Folder 8)
      - Franzosi, Roberto; Tilly, Charles. "British view of American strikes" (Box 68, Folder 9)
      - Koenker, Diane. "Strikes in Russia, 1917 a general review of the project" (report) (Box 68, Folder 10)
      - Lagrange, Hugues. "Crise et le conflit" (Box 68, Folder 11)
      - McClelland, Keith; Reid, Alastair. "Wood, iron and steel: technology, labour and trade union organization in the shipbuilding industry, 1840-1914" (Box 68, Folder 12)
      - Unidentified (Box 68, Folder 13)
    - Strikes, Social Conflict and the First World War
      (Manuscripts, drafts, typescripts and photocopies of typescripts of the articles contributed to the volume and papers presented at an international colloquium in Cortona in June 1986 many with manuscript corrections)
      - Table of content (Box 68, Folder 14)
      - Boch, Rudol"Changing pattersn of labor conflict and labor organization in the German cutlery industry Solingen 1905-1926" (Box 68, Folder 15)
      - Boll, Friedhelm. "Reformist and revolutionary strike practice in Germany labour disputes in Hanover and Braunschweig 1906-1919" (Box 68, Folder 16)
      - Costas, Ilse
        - "Management and labour in the Siemens plants in Berlin (1906-1920)" (Box 68, Folder 17)
        - "Siemens' management and labour in the First World War period (1906-1920)" (Box 68, Folder 17)
      - Feldman, Gerald D. "Introduction Germany" (Box 68, Folder 18)
        (including photocopy of a related letter from Gerald Feldman to Gioulio Sapelli, February 8, 1988)
      - Hardy-Emery, Odette. "Strikes in the Coal and Metal Basin of the Nord: new word force, new ideas. Three years of indecision: 1919-1921" (Box 68, Folder 19)
        (English and French)
      - Institute of International Labor Studies of the USSR Academy of Science. "Strike movement in Western countries after the October Revolution of 1917" (Box 69, Folder 1)
      - Kaelble, Hartmut. "International comparisons of the history of strikes" (Box 69, Folder 2)
      - Kir'ianov, Iurii:
        - "Strike movement in Russia in 1914- February 1917based on the materials of chronicles of workers' actions." (Box 69, Folder 3)
          (In Russian and English)
        - "Strike movement in Russia in1914-February 1917a discussion of statistical data" (Box 69, Folder 3)
      - Kunz, Andreas. "Patterns of labor unrest among state employees in Germany and Great Britain during and after the First World War (1917-1922)" (Box 69, Folder 4)
      - Mandel, Daniel. "Ivanovo-Kineshma region working class: a case study of the Russian labour movement in the province, 1914-1917" (Box 69, Folder 5)
      - Mueller, Dirk H. "Trade unions, workers' committees and workers' councils in Berlin's wartime industry 1914-1918" (Box 69, Folder 6)
      - Musso, Stefano. "Political tension and labor union struggle: working class conflicts n Turin during and after the First World War" (Box 69, Folder 7)
      - Perrot, Michelle. Translation of Introduction for Cortona volume (Box 69, Folder 8)
      - Potolov, Sergei Ivanovich. "Rabochee dvizhenie v Petrograde nakanune i v gody pervoi mirovoi voiny / Working-class movement in Petrograd on the Eve and during the First World War" (Box 69, Folder 9)
        (In English and Russian)
      - Procacci, Giovanna. "Changing nature of popular protest and labor unrest in Italy, 1917-1918the political content" (Box 69, Folder 10)
      - Pushkarev, I.M. "Rabochee dvizhenie v Rossii mezhdu fevralem i oktiabrem 1917 g.: o roli stachechnoi bor'by v politicheskoi kon'iunkture 1917 g. / Working-class movement in Russia between February and October 1917" (Box 69, Folder 11)
      - Quellien, Jean. "Working classes and strike movements in Lower Normandy during and after the First World War" (Box 69, Folder 12)
      - Robert, Jean-Louis. "Parisian strikes (August 1914 to July 1919)" (Box 70, Folder 1)
      - Sapelli, Giulio. "Strikes from 1789 to 1889" (Box 70, Folder 2)
      - Steinisch, Irmgard. "Patterns of labor conflicts among steel workers in Pittsburgh and in the Ruhr Valley after World War I: a comparative analysis" (Box 70, Folder 3)
      - Tomassini, Luigi. "Industrial mobilization and state intervention in Italy during World War I: effects on labor unrest" (Box 70, Folder 4)
      - Volkmann, Heinrich. "Strike waves of 1910-13 and 1919-20 in Germany. Continuity and discontinuity in the development of industrial conflict" (Box 70, Folder 5)
    - Strikes, Wars, and Revolutions in an International Perspective, (photocopy of typescript of the volume, with corrections)
      (incompleted. Arranged in accordance with pagination)
      - Manuscripts:
        - Tilly, Charles. "Theories and realities" (Box 70, Folder 6)
        - Haimson, Leopold. "Historical setting in Russia and the West" (Box 70, Folder 7)
        - Haimson, Leopold; Brian, Eric. "Introduction" (Box 70, Folder 8)
        - Boll, Friedhelm. "Changing forms of labor conflict: secular development or strike waves?" (Box 70, Folder 9)
        - Cronin, James. "Strikes and power in Britain, 1870-1920" (Box 70, Folder 10)
        - Haimson, Leopold; Petrusha, Ronald. "Two strike waves in Imperial Russia, 1905-19071912-1914" (Box 70, Folder 11)
        - Koenker, Diane; Rosenberg, William. "Strikes in revolution: Russia, 1917" (Box 70, Folder 12)
        - Lagrange, Hughes. "Crisis and conflict" (Box 70, Folder 13)
          (this manuscript wasn't included in the final version of the volume)
        - Bordogna, Lorenzo; Cella, Gian Primo; Provasi, Giancarlo. "Labor conflicts in Italy before the rise of fascism, 1881-1923a quantitative analysis" (Box 70, Folder 14)
        - Edwards, P.K. "Strikes and politics in the United States, 1900-1919" (Box 70, Folder 15)
        - Montgomery, David. "Strikes of machinists in the United States, 1870-1922" (Box 70, Folder 16)
        - Domansky, Elizabeth. "Rationalization of class struggle: strikes and strike strategy of the German Metal Workers' Union from 1891-1922" (Box 71, Folder 1)
        - Hogan, Heather. "Scientific management and the changing nature of work in the St. Petersburg metalworking industry, 1900-1914" (Box 71, Folder 2)
        - Tilly, Charles. "Introduction" (Box 71, Folder 3)
        - Boll, Friedhelm. "Economic cycles and labor conflicts in Germany during the first quarter of the twentieth century" (Box 71, Folder 4)